Hey guys, welcome back. So till now we
have seen producer, topic, partition,
segments, then broker, cluster,
controller,
kft.
Okay. And uh yeah, ISR insync replicas.
Now let's again uh but I will uh stitch
all the points. So complete flow. Okay.
So first I'm going to show you complete
producer right flow. Let's say topic is
created uh with the help of controller
and metadata is present. Okay. Metadata
information is present to all the
brokers. That is done. Okay. Now after
that complete producer write flow. Let's
see this flow once.
Okay. So step one,
let me zoom it a bit. Producer creates
event. So this is the
publish message that hey
topic which I want to publish. This is
the key and this is the value which I
want to store and
acknowledge equals to all which will
help in determining ISR. Okay.
So now what will happen? So every step I
want you to pause and see what will
happen. We just like whatever we have
seen till now we are just clubbing it
together. So in step two what would
happen? So producer uh producer have
this uh event which it need to publish.
What it will do? So producer request
metadata first time or when it refresh
its metadata because why it need
metadata. See producer need to invoke
the broker
in a cluster there are many brokers.
Which broker it need to invoke? It need
to invoke the broker
which has let's say particular partition
leader.
Okay. and how it determine which
partition through key.
Okay. So first thing is that it need to
have certain metadata information and
what this metadata information is that
okay this topic this partition who is
the who has the leader which broker has
the leader
okay now let's say in this example
what it will do is producer will ask any
broker hey give me the metadata
information okay generally
broker like I told you right controller
pass the metadata information cluster
metadata information to all the brokers
so broker save it but many times it
happen is that it got expired and all so
if broker doesn't have it they pass the
request to active controller active
controller gives the metadata response
to the broker and broker ultimately goes
give the response to the producer hey
this is the metadata detail so metadata
detail has like okay for this topic this
partition this broker is the leader for
this partition this is the this broker
is the leader okay now this metadata
information is present with the producer
step three it will calculate the
partition so partition it will calculate
that hash of this key
modulo the number of partition within
this topic so for now let's say that we
have three three partition so what is
the partition partition we got one
partition number one. So who is the
leader of the partition one? Broker two.
So in step four
okay what it will do is that it will
find out that from this metadata
I need to publish this event
to this partition
who is the leader. So it will find out
broker two is the leader. Now what will
what it will do is it will directly
invoke the broker to
okay and will ask it to write this
event. So in step six broker to write
event to its partition one log. So you
know already right? So topic let's say
order - events then you have partition
one you wanted to write right? Partition
one might have segment. In segment, it
will write this new event.
New event at offset 101. It write.
Now when broker 2 has written it, it
will check hey
producer has used acknowledge all means
it will check the ISR list
and it will wait for all the replicas
which are there to respond that they
have successfully written also. So since
acknowledge equals to all broker 2 will
wait for all the ISR to update the
events. So we have let's say ISR has
broker one, broker two, broker three,
broker two has the leader which has
already returned. Now it will wait for
broker one and broker three also which
are followers. So once they do
poll f the latest update and acknowledge
it after return successfully.
Okay, when all the ISR acknowledge that
they have done then it will send the
respond back to the producer that event
is published successfully.
Okay,
write flow is clear.
Now let's see consumer read flow.
Okay, step one, consumer starts and want
to join a particular group. Let's say I
want to join a group ID notification
service.
Okay. Now what it will do is a step two
find the partition number of topic. See
everything is handled by broker the
server Kafka server. Okay. Consumer and
producer are just client.
Now if any consumer want to join a group
who will add server will add right but I
told you if you remember okay uh for
let's say you have a group consumer
group let's say notification consumer
group analytics okay and you have 50
partitions
of consumer offset topic you have 50
partition we have already seen that.
So this group information is handled by
one of the partition out of this 50.
Okay, because the formula was hash of
group ID mod 50. So let's say you got
partition 23. So partition 23 will
handle all the
requests for this group. So that's where
I am finding out that okay which
partition
and why it has to find out a partition
number because in case of cluster we
have multiple brokers.
Okay. So broker one, broker two, broker
three, one of the broker
host this partition as a leader.
Partition 23 is a leader here and broker
two. So this consumer need to invoke
this broker. Right? So that's what it is
doing. First it need to find out like
what is the partition number which uh
and then only it would be able to find
out the specific broker which is hold
the leader replica of the partition 23.
So it will find out like hash of
notification service group ID mod 50.
Let's say I got 23. So partition 23 of
topic this is what
can handle you can say that uh handle
this group
details.
Now in step three what would happen is
consumer also need metadata information
like how consumer will get to know that
okay this broker holds this partition as
leader and this is as followers. So it
needs certain metadata the same as
producer. So it will ask any broker hey
return me the metadata. If broker
doesn't have it it will ask controller.
Controller will return the metadata
response because see this is cluster
information about topic about partition
about broker. These are cluster
information. That's why it is going to
the controller. Okay. So which broker
holds which topic and
which partition as leader which
partition as follower this is cluster
information okay and that's why
currently at this point of time consumer
is interested in this cluster
information that hey who holds this
because it need to find out the leader
for this partition. So first it is
fetching the cluster metadata.
So it ask any broker any broker will
goes to the controller if it doesn't
have then uh it goes to the controller
controller returns the information and
ultimately consumer get it. So consumer
knows that okay for this topic consumer
offset topic
partition zero
holds by broker one partition two leader
is broker two and let's say partition 23
broker three contains the leader
replica.
Okay. Now in step four what it will do?
It will invoke. See now you are
interested in this 23 right. I told you
that only leader replica can write and
can read. Okay. So it can't just send to
any broker. Let's say even broker 2 has
the follower. Let's say follower of
partition 23. But it can't invoke broker
2. It has partition 23 follower.
Follower can't write.
Okay. So that's why it need to goes to
the leader
broker.
So now in the step four it invokes
broker three and that generally broker
no in case of consumer known as group
coordinator. I told you that why it
known as group coordinator because let's
say if your group is this consumer group
is notification
it will always comes like same partition
partition 23 because formula is like
hash of group ID mod 50 okay and let's
say one particular broker host this as a
leader so this broker is known as group
coordinator so always for this group
request come to this broker only because
this host the leader for this partition.
Okay. So you can say that partition is
just a way of distributing the load to
uh multiple servers.
So yes now broker 3 will got this
request. Okay. And the request is that
this consumer wants to join the
notification service group. So what it
will do, okay,
in step five, broker 3, it will update
its metadata.
Okay, and you remember like for consumer
the metadata information is like where
it is stored.
It is stored under consumer
offset. All information regarding
consumer is stored in this. See consumer
related information is not cluster
metadata. It never goes till controller.
Okay. This consumer
is part of this group. This consumer
takes care of this partition. This is
not cluster information. Okay. So all
this information is stored within this
topic itself.
So that's what it does. Okay. So it what
it this group coordinator will do is it
will update its consumer metadata. You
can say that and it will say that okay
let's say consumer 3 is the new consumer
which it wanted to add. So what it will
do is it will add into this group. Okay,
for this group, this topic, hey this
consumer, you take care of partition
two. It will assign one partition to it.
Okay, so broker 3 waits
because
in producer you know that whenever the
broker writes it will check acknowledge
equals to all
or acknowledge equals to zero or
acknowledge equals to 1. It will wait
for replicas within ISR.
But in when the consumer does that there
is nothing like acknowledge equals to
all or it pass it do not pass anything.
Consumer do not pass anything. So what
happen is by default for consumer it act
as an all. Okay. So what it happen is it
will wait all the rep like you can say
that all the brokers which hold this
partition 23 replica
it will wait for it so that they also
update this information that okay in
this group I am adding this new consumer
and this consumer will take care of the
partition two of this topic. So this
information will get stored into the
leader which is a group coordinator.
Okay. And also all the followers of the
partition 23.
So once that is done like consumer is
added to the group the next step is
see consumer let's say consumer three it
is assigned partition two. Now it need
to know okay what is the last fetch
offset for this one. It is possible that
some previous consumer was there it got
crashed and this consumer got the
responsibility. So we need to find out
that one right. What is the last offset
for the partition two has been
processed.
So again
it will goes to where? It will goes to
the group coordinator only. Okay. And
who is the group coordinator? You can
find out like okay u the same formula it
will use hash of group ID mod 50. You
will get partition 23. From the metadata
it will see that okay partition 23 is
hold by broker 3. So broker 3 is
ultimately get the call.
So for one group always request goes to
you can say that one broker you can say
that one. So that's why they are known
as group coordinator. Now this group
coordinator what it will do is it will
look at the consumer offset.
Okay. And internally it will check for
the key that hey this is the group ID.
Okay. This is the group ID. This is the
topic. This is the partition.
Okay. And it find the value the last
offset read
and it will return it.
Now what would happen is now it got that
okay from 101 I need to start. Now next
step what it will do is that it will
invoke the leader broker. So now see it
is interested in topic order events
partition two. Okay, because this is
this is the partition it has been
assigned to is right partition two for
the order events
and it need to know that it need to
fetch from 101.
Now from this metadata in this metadata
it also have information about this
topic this topic this partition who is
the leader let's say leader is broker
two in this case broker two hosts the
leader replica of this partition two. So
it will call broker 2 directly
and it will say that hey fetch me from
101 and return me 200 bytes. Okay we can
configure this at a time consumer how
many data how many record it want to
pull based on memory it want to record
200 byt in a one shot. So what this
broker will do which is the leader of
this partition two of order event it
will return the offset in sequential way
from 101 let's say till 501 becomes 200
bytes. So it will return this many
events.
Now what it will do is it will start
processing those. Now once it process it
need to commit also. Okay. So what it
will do is that let's say I am following
manual approach and batch like after
this all one batch is completed then
only I'm doing commit. So once I
processed all what I am doing is again I
need to go to coordinator because all
consumer related information is stored
in consumer offset. Okay.
And uh this consumer offset has multiple
partition again and one of the partition
it has to store this because partition
is just a way to distribute the load
among brokers.
So
once it has to do the commit what it
will do is that it knows that okay for
this uh group notification group my
partition is 23. From this metadata it
know that broker 3 is the
leader which host partition 23 of
consumer offset. Okay. So it will reach
to the broker three which act as a group
coordinator for this group notification
group and it will write into its
consumer offset partition 23.
Okay, consumer offset partition 23 it
will add into it segment file let's say
okay that it process till 5001
and once it is done
the consumer continue do the polling so
one thing you get to know that consumer
in Kafka consumers are poll based not
pushbased
so Kafka is not pushbased it's was poll
this consumer keep on polling and it
will goes to the step eight again
that it will again ask the
order events to fetch me another 200
bytes start from let's say 501
okay and once it is uh start from 502
because 501 is already done so from 502
give me another 200 bytes from offset
502 give me another 200 bytes and just
keep on flowing.
So consumer read flow is also clear like
here
we have seen the end to end flow what
consumer will do.
Okay. Now one thing
is log compaction strategy.
So we know that Kafka is keep on
appending
the event into its file.
So when it deleted
or when it uh what's the strategy
to remove it or something? So there are
two policy one is delete which is
default. So it deletes the old segment
based on time or size. We can define
both. So in configuration I can do this
cleanup policy is delete which I want to
go. Retention is let's say 7 days I want
to give. So you can give in millisecond
that this is the retention time and you
can also give the bytes 1 GB I want to
have the maximum size. So what would be
the behavior? Let's say you know that
everything is stored within a segments.
So it's this rules applies on segments
you can say partition segment. So when a
particular segments is created let's say
8 days ago it would get deleted because
the maximum retention time you have
given 7 days. So it always works on
segments.
Okay. Let's say if any segment is just
created 6 days ago, it would be kept. It
won't get deleted.
Similarly, the size based like uh you
have defined 1 GB. So now let's say that
segment one is 1 GB, segment 2 is 200
GB. Total is 1.2GB. So it is greater
than 1 GB. Okay. Uh for a particular
partition, what would happen is it will
delete the old segment. So it will
delete the older segment. 1 GB it will
delete it.
Okay. So it remember always this works
on segment level of a partition.
Another policy is compact
and again it is an async job. It do not
happen in a synchronous manner. The
compact. So compact is like you can do
cleanup. Policy equals to compact. Now
understand this. Let's say in a segment.
So whenever we publish
an event okay so you know that we have
let's say topic
and key
okay and the JSON record so the key is
something if you have provided the key
then this compact can be an h for so
generally let's say in the segment
record is like hey offset 100 the key is
your let's Say user one and the record
is your let's say version one
next event comes offset is 101 user two
which is a key here and the record is
let's say whatever the JSON let's say
version one like this you have so what
happen is there is a you can say that a
background job which keep on running on
this segments and try to do a compaction
what compaction means is keep the
latest
value of
a particular key. So now let's say key
is user one. So user one has yes one two
times. So it will keep the latest value
102. User 1 v2 the older one get
removed. Similarly user two does it has
duplicate? Yes. User two it will keep
the latest one 101 only 104 version two.
User three has only one entry. So that
will cap. So it compacted. So it again
happen at segment level. For each
segment it does happen in unsynchronous.
Do not block rightes. Okay. And yes
since it is happening as synchronous
immediate cleanup doesn't happen.
Okay. So that is done.
Now one more very important question.
And one doubt which definitely might
have comes to your mind. Hey, Kafka is
reading and writing from disk. Isn't
disk read and writes are slow? How Kafka
is so fast? So generally there are two
ways it makes itself fast. One is at the
time of write and one is at the time of
read. So at the time of write it follow
page cache optimization.
Okay. So just say that Kafka trust OS
caching strategy. Okay. To keep the
caching effectively for the files.
So now let's say leader particular
leader broker is writing to a disk.
What it will do is it will first store
into a RAM OS page cache. In the
operating system you might have read it
OS page cache okay and asynchronally it
flush the data to the disk
okay so it don't directly write to the
disk it first write into the RAM and
asynchronously it write to the disk so
no blocking disk weight and sequential
while so whenever you are writing to a
disk right you can say that it always
happen in sequential In case of Kafka
which is very very important and this is
the best case for disk and why for Kafka
sequential write happen because Kafka is
append only I told you Kafka is append
only no insertion in mid never modify
old data never update record in place it
only writes at end whenever any event
new event come it create a new offset
incremental let's say 32 write it offset
33 write it so always sequential
Okay. So d keep moving forward. So
always sequential write it support.
So that's one way of optimization
during write. Okay. So disk right happen
in a synchronous manner. First it write
to the RAM in the OS page cache.
Now during read
it follow zero copy optimization.
So generally let's say if you are not
following zero copy optimization what
happen is let's say your file is present
into disk and when you load it it first
load into RAM OS page cache from there
it loads into your application JVM user
space and might there it goes to the
network okay but Kafka make use of
system call send file it do not even
load into your user space So Kafka
servers might be running. So let's say
Kafka JVM space you can say it do not
even load or copy the data
to its user space. So it say that hey it
directly make a system called send file.
So from disk it goes to the OS page
cache and directly goes to the network.
No copies maintained in Kafka JVM.
Okay. So it saves one hop during the
read. So it not only uh save hop you can
say that data copy time from this to
user space not only save speed but also
memory CPU cycles are also saved and got
high throughput. So during read and
write both Kafka perform certain
optimization.
Okay.
So in next part I will show some failure
scenarios and how it would be handled
but I hope I am not rushing and going
slowly and uh this flows now makes sense
to pictureize end to end flow. What
happened during when producer write the
event? What happened when consumer read
the event? Okay pause it go through it
again things will start making sense and
any doubt let me know we can discuss
further. Bye.